Heat.
[Music]
[Applause]
A million dollars,
16 machines,
and they went slower. They lost. It was
a race, a database race. Best
implementation
verse interface. You'd think the fast
code would win. The better engine.
But the real power is never under the
hood. It's in the design, in the
thinking, in the interface.
Interfaces are powerful. They are the
boundaries where our components interact
to exchange information through the
function signatures exposed by our
implementation. But as boundaries,
interfaces are not only what's exposed
but what's imposed. Uh and therefore not
only how our systems talk but how they
scale. uh as engineers we tend to think
of performance in terms of systems
coding uh so all the low-level
techniques uh but I want to convince you
uh that these techniques pale in
comparison to the power of systems
thinking uh so to convince you of this I
want to give us a challenge uh we're
going to take one of the world's most
valuable workloads in existence today uh
and we're going to show from theory and
practice. First that popular database
management systems have a performance
limit uh for this workload. Uh second
that this performance limit is a
property of the interface not the
implementation. So that no amount of
optimization or hardware no amount of
hardware whether vertical or horizontal
will make these systems faster. And
third uh that this limit is far lower
than we think and easy to hit. Uh so
having established this from theory and
practice uh that the interface more than
code or compute sets the speed limit um
we're going to find a way uh by fixing
only the interface uh to make the system
10 times a thousand times faster to
prove the power of an interface for
performance and not because we feel the
need uh the need for speed uh or because
it's our duty uh but because the world
demands it. Uh so before we continue, uh
just a heads up, uh we're going to start
slow. Uh we're going to finish fast. Uh
and that flash photography
is allowed. Uh but you might want to
have your camera ready. You might want
to get it out and have it ready when the
time comes. So are you ready?
>> Great. So I said it's a challenge. Uh
because the interface I have in mind for
us, it's valuable. Uh it's seen a ton of
scrutiny. uh it's been Jeepson a
thousand times over. Uh we're going to
have to find something hiding in plain
sight um that will look obvious in
hindsight and especially because when
you think of a database uh it's hard to
find an interface more powerful than
SQL. Um but the interface we're going to
look at uh it's more than SQL. So it's
the intersection of SQL and I'm being
very specific here. So this is not a
problem with SQL. It's a problem at the
intersection of SQL across the network
uh for transaction processing or OOLTP.
Uh so the workload executes transactions
across the network between two or more
rows to update counts. We're computing
counts as goods and services move from
one person or place to another. And in
parallel to the movement of these goods
and services, uh money is changing
hands. This is not about SQL or
networking in a general purpose LGP uh
or analytical OLAP uh context to store
user tables or product tables or to run
reporting. None of the control plane or
data science workloads uh like signing
up a user, updating a product catalog or
querying parquet. Uh rather the tables
we have in view are strictly a subset of
the tables you might find in a general
purpose database. So not the low volume
tables but the high volume tables and
specifically the inventory counts the
shopping cart items the checkout
payments the deliveries the refunds the
ratings all the data plane processing
that is black Friday. Uh if OLAP is uh
read heavy uh then OLTP is right heavy.
Uh so the field of transaction
processing was pioneered by Turing award
winner Jim Gray. Um he's regrettably no
longer with us. Uh 50 years ago at IBM
he worked on system R the first
implementation of SQL. 42 years ago with
Andreas Reuter uh Jim coined the term
acid and later wrote the book on OLTP.
uh but 40 years ago uh this year Jim
Gray would define a measure of
transaction processing power in this
paper which he published under tandem
not his own name. Benchmark wars were
risky business at the time. Uh so the
paper would do two things as I said
first kickstart a benchmark war uh that
would actually sometimes we need these
things we we get stuck with performance
and then we actually need to go faster.
Uh so this is what this paper did. It it
got databases to get order of magnitude
uh faster as a result. Um because this
paper would encourage databases not only
to be correct but to be correct and
fast. Uh and the paper accomplished
that. Uh the second thing this paper
accomplished was that Jim Gray would
define the unit of a transaction. What
is a transaction? And this unit was a
debit credit uh which remained his
measure of transactions per second ever
since. So there's some fascinating
papers reflecting back on this 20 years
later. One that he wrote, others that
people wrote in tribute to Jim Gray all
talking about this. It's so wonderful to
read, you know, the their reflections.
Dvet or um authors one of these papers
just so much wonderful anecdotes in
there all about Jim Gray. But all
through his life, you know what is the
unit of a transaction? A debit credit.
So simple yet powerful. And powerful
because you can express the movement of
anything, anything in life, the movement
of anything from one entity to another.
Uh the essence of a transaction. What
does it mean to transact? It's to move
something. And if this sounds simple, I
think that's because it is. uh so to
debit one row or account and to uh
credit another. So in pseudo code uh
Gray wrote this out says to update two
accounts insert a record of the history
of the transfer and then he did
something subtle.
This is often missed in industry in
research. It's incredibly subtle. Can
you see what it is?
He introduced the concept of a branch.
doesn't mean anything by itself but it's
essentially a hot account. So every
transaction is going to go through this
hot account and it will be involved in
some percentage of transactions. In
other words, contention. So contention
is where multiple transactions need to
update the same rows forcing the
database to serialize or coordinate
them. Uh for example, here are 53
accounts or rows. These are just rows in
a in a table. uh if we do double entry
transactions between pairs of rows but
none of these uh transactions intersect
then there's no contention uh
transactions can be executed by the
database in parallel.
But if we now process 34 transactions
and 17 of them all hit the company bank
account or income account or a stock
item that's a bestseller contention is
now at 50%. So you sometimes hear even
database engineers describe this as
pathological. Uh I I've actually had a
very senior database engineer wanted to
um you know interview with Tiger Beetle.
They were from a very well-known
database company and they said to me,
"Oh, this workload is pathological." And
I thought that's interesting, you know,
because Jim Gray didn't recognize
contention um as essential to the OLTP
workload just to make it hard for us as
database engineers. He he wasn't trying
to be pathological. or rather he was
saying this is this is the real world
out there for OOLTP to make it realistic
uh because the more people who want the
same thing at the same time uh the worse
this gets uh and cues build up uh so
these are the big scale events if you
think of big scale think of contention
uh you can't really handle big scale if
you can't handle contention so you get a
a super node in your graph and
contention approaches 90% so you can
imagine 14 million people last year
trying to get tickets for Oasis. Uh and
it sold out in minutes. Uh there's
always some degree of contention, but
the more popular a platform gets and the
more scale it attracts, uh the more you
see the power law kicking in as power
users flock to the platform. So you get
these super nodes in the graph. Another
name for the power law is the Pareto
principle uh where 80% of transactions
say just as an example they might be by
20% of users 80% of volume is from a
small set of power users and you tend to
find the purto principle or power law
everywhere uh in all kinds of
transaction workloads. You can go on to
uh Wikipedia and it's amazing you know
how many studies there are where you
actually see in all of life you know
biology um geography there's there's
these these things that tend to dominate
um but in trading um if you take the
trading volume say for NASDAQ uh and
look at the top super stocks so Nvidia
Microsoft Apple Amazon Google you know
depending on the day they can dominate
volumes together
the result of the Power law in general
is a large volume of transactions
flowing through a small proportion of
rows in the database locking these rows
locking performance for as long as the
locks are held. Uh so Jim Gray
understood uh that our OOLTP benchmark
should reflect contention because a
database transaction represents a debit
credit in the real world. Uh and indeed
if we trace the family tree of databases
they more or less go back uh to the
banking, the brokerage, airline
manufacturing, inventory, ordering uh
shipping systems that did the equivalent
of debit credit as original workload,
high volume but routine. Uh these are
not the complex queries of general
purpose analytics. Not trying to get
data out of the database. They're just
trying to put transactions in, put data
in. very routine high volume. So this
pattern laid the foundation for OLTP.
Today in industry and research we tend
to forget this but transactions are all
around us everywhere uh and they've been
increasing in volume. So in the last 7
to 10 years transaction volumes across
gaming uh energy even ride sharing they
increase two to three orders of
magnitude. In the extreme, real time
transactions or instant payments are up
four orders of magnitude or 10,000x
from what they were 10 years ago. Uh
Jeff Dean has a saying that you design
for 10 10x growth but plan to rewrite
before 100x. Uh so if our transaction
volumes are up, you know, how are we
doing with our planning? Do our
databases have enough power uh to
process these volumes? Uh so to answer
the question uh we're going to use the
debit credit measure of transaction
power as defined by Jim Gray. We're
going to benchmark four databases. Uh
two with the same interface but
different implementation and then two
with a different interface. Uh so we're
going to look at the power of an
interface to unlock performance. But
first, we're going to look at uh the
power of an interface to lock
performance. Uh and to do that, we're
going to start with the crowd favorite.
Any guesses? Postgress. So, world's most
popular general purpose database by far.
Postgres, our first contestant. You see
echoes of Jim Gray's understanding of
debit credit in the Postgres docs uh in
their canonical example of a
transaction. However, uh the example
here collapses debit and credit columns
into a single balance. So, it's single
entry, not double entry. And it doesn't
insert a record of the transfer as
history. So, it loses information. Uh
so, instead, for our challenge, uh
here's how we're going to represent Jim
Gray's debit credit, his measure of
transaction processing power. So, first
we do a round trip across the network.
We ask the database for Alice and Bob's
account.
Uh then we move this data back to the
code uh where we check in variance. For
example, does Alice have enough money
and maybe has Bob not been paid enough
times in all these examples. Uh uh if
the roundtrip time is 1 millisecond uh
then the query takes one millisecond
there and back again. Uh next we send
another query to the database uh to add
to Alice's debits column and to add to
Bob's credits column uh and insert a
record of the transfer as history.
taking another millisecond across the
network. Uh if we assume the database is
infinitely fast, infinitely fast. Um
that's how much time it takes and that's
it. Um so this is what's called an
interactive transaction uh because the
application interacts with the database
across the network uh with multiple
queries u to move the data to the code.
Uh when you look at real systems, they
might do more logic. Uh so there may be
more than two queries. uh as many as 10
in real systems even for an optimal
system. And while you can do this in one
shot in one query, it's not common. Um
the two queries here also mirror uh the
two messages in Jim Gray's uh pseudo
code. Uh first to read the accounts and
then to write them back plus a history.
So I think this strikes the sweet spot.
Uh not as easy as one shot yet not as
hard as it could be. Uh so if we send
this workload into Postgress a whole lot
of transactions concurrently how many
transactions per second do you think
Postgres will do?
Okay. So I think 12,000 debit credits a
second should be enough for anyone.
Okay. Well this is fine.
Uh, but what's happening? 41.
I'm not I I'm not clicking anything.
So, we're not changing anything in the
application or database here. Uh, but
over time, uh, a few power users started
showing up. Our workload shifted
dynamically outside the database,
outside the application to a few hot
accounts and our DBA moved one of our
database clients from 1 millisecond away
to 10 milliseconds away. Uh so did you
expect contention and network latency to
impact Postgress throughput like this?
Uh let's take a closer look. Uh so here
we've got a Postgress server in Europe.
Amsterdam doesn't have much space. We
tried to get one here but we had to
settle for Frankfurt. Uh so all the
database clients are one millisecond
away. Um and as we increase contention
from zero to 10% contention, 10% of
transactions are hitting the same
account, same row, as we go from 10% to
50% to 90% contention, uh we see
throughput drop, I think this makes
sense. Uh but the surprising thing is
how sensitive the Postgres interface is
to network latency. Uh you know where we
position the clients. So here we move
the clients to be 10 milliseconds away
from the server. Um and this reduces
throughput significantly. Uh but worse
far away clients are now affecting the
throughput of clients nearby. So the
whole system is horribly intertwined. Uh
if you look closer at the interface, can
you see the problem?
More specifically,
locks are being held. Uh they're halting
throughput not only while transactions
are being processed. This is the rub. Uh
while not only while they're being
processed in the database, but also
while while the database waits on the
application to make a decision to
commit. So this means waiting on a
network roundtrip uh to send the
accounts to the application and then
wait for the application to send the
commit. In other words, this transaction
locks these rows for how long?
1 millisecond. Uh if your network round
trip is 1 millisecond, but if your
network round trip is 10 millisecond,
now your transaction locks these for 10
milliseconds. Why? Um you know there's a
law to describe this effect though. Uh
you see it typically applied in parallel
computing. uh but AMDall's law states
that even with massive parallel
processing the maximum speed up we can
achieve will be ultimately constrained
by the serial or contended portion of
the workload that will dominate. Uh so
the law takes two variables just two uh
the time that a transaction holds locks
the percentage contention in the
workload. The law takes two variables
and then it plugs it into a simple
formula to tell you the theoretical
speed limit. The scary thing is that
even if your database is infinitely
fast, infinitely parallel um you know
and AMDL's law assumes that it is uh
even so if the roundtrip is 1
millisecond and if contention is only
one millisecond uh then the theoretical
speed limit is 100,000 transactions per
second if your database is infinitely
fast.
uh but as contention increases just 10%
uh throughput drops um not by 10% but by
10 times so as you go from 0% contention
to 10% contention you lost 10x
throughput uh now you're at 10,000 TPS
uh at 50% contention
our theoretical top speed is 2,000 TPS
uh with power law contention our top
speed is a1 111 TPS. Theoretically, your
database is infinitely fast, infinitely
parallel. This is your you you cannot
beat this theory. Uh and and that's just
with a network latency of 1 millisecond.
Uh but if your clients are 10
milliseconds away from the database,
this drops throughput another 10x.
Let's do that again. Now we're at 10,000
TPS with 10% contention. Then a,000.
Then 200. And finally 111 TPS is our
maximum theoretical top speed for the
postgris interface. And again these
speed limits assume that your database
is infinitely parallel and infinitely
fast. I will never need to do more than
111 TPS they say uh because that is
actually now the speed limit. So at this
point we should note that we're not the
first to see that there's a major
problem uh with the general purpose
database interface for OLTP. uh that you
hit this hard asmmptote uh when you hold
blocks across the network. Um
unfortunately you sometimes see two
responses here uh where making tradeoffs
instead of challenging assumptions uh
people give up on Jim Gay's vision of
correct and fast. They fall for the
temptation to be correct but not fast or
fast but not correct. So for example uh
they say that we should shift
responsibility for scale from the
database where it's traditionally been
to the app and then they say that the
app shouldn't update the same key
concurrently. you you shouldn't you know
you shouldn't be booking Oasis some
other app should do that uh but not your
app you know and they will say scalable
apps did did you notice that they like a
scalable app it's almost it's really
shifting that that responsibility I I
really hate that phrase when someone
says scalable app as a database
developer like no the platform should be
scalable we shouldn't be sherking our
responsibility to the apps the apps are
stateless we are supposed to be scaling
our state as databases
But they say scalable apps must avoid
contention as if they even can. This is
the real workload, you know, and or they
say that you should trade acid.
Trade just trade asset. Trade those
guarantees for performance to relax the
eye in acid. Kyle was sort of hinting at
this. You know these relaxed weakened
isolation levels. People actually say
you should do this. Um I don't think we
should listen to them. Uh but because
what what they are essentially saying is
you know let the transactions use the
wrong numbers and you will get more
performance. Um but give me serializable
or give me death because if you can't
count correctly with contention at high
speed it's not OLTP. Uh and if you're
not doing serializable uh if you're
cutting corners on isolation it's not
acid. So it's not it's not OLTP or it's
not acid. You know, as Uncle Ben would
say, uh those who would trade safety for
performance deserve neither safety nor
performance because you will never get
performance by giving up acid. It you
can try it, but you you're not going to
go much faster. You know, maybe a little
bit, but it's wrong. Uh so I think
that's true. until we challenge our
assumptions, until I learn to think, you
know, for myself, um I'm not going to be
able to apply first principles to
discover that there's a third way out.
Um, of course, in spite of everything
we've said, uh, someone will suggest
that there's a fourth way out uh that
you can make a trade-off between theory,
uh, and horizontal scalability. So that
the problem is really just Postgress uh,
the specific implementation of Postgres.
But if you use one of the newer cloud
databases with a different
implementation, uh then you can buy I
mean you can add machines to scale
horizontally. And by I mean add as many
machines as you like. And I quote for
unlimited
infinite scale.
We've anonymized these vendors. You will
never be able to guess who they are.
This sounds exciting. This is more
ambitious than a thousandx. A thousandx
is child's play. It is so humble,
unlimited, infinite. And perhaps it
sounds a bit expensive. But what if we
swap out implementation and and see what
happens? Uh because the advantage of all
these databases being wire compatible
with postcris as they are is that the
interface is the same and therefore you
can control the experiment. Uh so what
we're going to do is pick one of these
to be contestant number two. I'm not
going to tell you which one. uh because
it's not open source uh and because the
findings apply more or less to all of
them uh and there are quite a few of
them uh but we're going to launch a
cluster that's fully managed on their
cloud platform. They're going to run it
for us. Um and you can do this with
almost any Postgres provider out there.
So the database looks like Postgres and
talks like Postgres with the same
interface but otherwise it's a
completely independent implementation.
So where postgres runs on one machine uh
this runs on many which is supposed to
give you more scale. So to embrace
infinite scale uh we ordered the largest
possible cluster which immediately
collided with finite procurement. So the
next biggest we could get was 16
machines costing $84,000
a month uh or just over a million dollar
a year. To be honest, we had goosebumps.
Uh, and and I've anonymized these specs
a little bit so you can really not
guess, you know, which provider this is.
Uh,
but we had goosebumps because, you know,
the same amount of money would buy you a
McLaren. Uh, but does it scale? Uh, so
we revved it up. Uh, we took it for a
test drive. It felt amazing. We ran the
same LTP workload. Uh this was through
the same interface but now powered by a
millionoll cluster and the results were
stunning.
Okay, before I show you the results,
let's think about it. So remember
30-year-old Postgres on a single
machine, very cheap, could do a speed,
you know, top speed of 12,000 debit
credits a second, no contention. What do
we expect from a modern rewrite
state-of-the-art rewrite running on 16
times as many machines?
>> 10x. Who says 10x? I'm saying 10x.
Who says worse? Raise your hands.
Who didn't raise their hand?
Okay. 7,000 TPS.
Um, zero contention. So we couldn't do
10x, but we could do a little more than
half. Uh uh so the the best we could do
was 7,524
transactions a second. And to be clear,
these numbers were produced under
identical workloads and controlled
conditions. We're going to say a little
bit more about this later. Uh perhaps
someone might say that this is just the
cost of consensus. In other words, you
know, that little split-second automated
failover that happens only when the
primary machine crashes. There shouldn't
be any uh leader election going on here.
We're not crushing machines. Uh the
cluster is stable. It's only doing
replication within the same data center.
These days, you get a ton of network
bandwidth. We might expect a four to 5%
hit from replication. This is what you
typically measure. But not a 40 to 50%
hit like this. Um there's got to be
something else going on. Um now we've
increased contention to 10%.
Before it was 0% contention, we were
half Postgress. Now we're a little bit
more realistic. 10% contention and we've
lost 10x performance. We're now at 574
transactions a second. This is fine,
they say, because our company will never
do more than 574 transactions a second.
But the good news of horizontal scaling
is that the cluster is elastic. So you
can change the number of machines to
increase scale while decreasing cost to
do more with less. Uh here we've
decreased the number of machines. We've
cut cost by 50%. We've increased
performance by 10%. This is staff
engineering. We've cut our McLaren in
half and our engines revving faster than
before. So let's put the pedal to the
metal and scale to one machine. This is
principal engineering. We've decreased
costs by eight times and increased
performance by 30%. You know, if we put
this all together and plot more
contention uh for 50% and 90% power law,
then we see that a cluster of one beats
a McLaren. Uh but if we plot Amdal's
law, then you really start to see that
all these curves follow the theory, the
same shape. If the interface imposes a
speed limit, then all the money in the
world can't overcome the asmtote. But if
all that was left of you was your smile
and some systems thinking, you can scale
the world with your little finger. So
you don't need a McLaren. Understanding
is worth more. Uh to be clear, this is
bigger than Postgres. It's even bigger
than SQL for that matter. So SQL is just
a query language. Doesn't say anything
about rollocks. Even if SQL replaced
with a better spec, um if your database
is general purpose to move the data to
the code, uh then you need coordination
in some shape or form and this is what
invokes Amdoll's law because the network
trip uh that roundtrip time is never
going to change. Uh speed of light and
fibers are constant. So right contention
is the Achilles heel in the OOLTP
workload. It's what separates OLTP from
OOLGP. uh the volume of rights and the
contention of these rights. But the
worst uh is that if we measure one level
deeper, if we put our McLaren back
together and we take a look at those
engines, they were never revving.
Just 10% contention, the machines are
idle. A million dollars of hardware is
idle at 12% CPU. Of course uh someone
will insist that we should have tried
harder to saturate the CPU that we
should have used
static memory allocation zero
dialization zero copy direct memory
access memory locality cach line
alignment explicit limits concurrency
parallelism pipeline scheduling hardware
acceleration branch prediction
vectorzation loop on rolling profiling
watch more Casey and maybe if we had
rewritten the database in uh so I went
looking for Mike Actton one of the
proponents of data oriented design I
went looking for Mike. And I went to
Maui
and I also got the shirt.
[Applause]
Um
but the point is that not even the most
powerful techniques uh we use as systems
coders. Not even the most powerful
systems techniques like data oriented
design is they can't overcome a bad
interface if the interface is the
bottleneck. So we're going to have to
take this off and find another way. Uh
because especially with a fast
implementation if it can drive the CPU
then you need to throw a lot of
information at it to saturate it and for
that you need a powerful interface. Uh
so to go from 80% to 90 from 10x to a
th00and uh we need more than systems
coding we need systems thinking uh to
fix the interface and break the sound
barrier. So how can we fix the
interface? Uh by now someone is asking
what are they asking but what about
>> store procedures
>> stored procedures. Thank you.
So why not replace the queries you know
with custom functions in the database.
Uh so we transact in a single roundtrip
across the network but without rollocks
to this I say let's take it a step
further. You know with stored procedures
we still have to cross the network to
call them. What if we didn't have to?
What would be cooler than stored
procedures?
And the answer of course putting the
Amsterdam in OLAP. Uh contestant number
three is
duct DB. Yeah. An embedded analytical
database that runs in process. So
there's no network. So you transact
directly against the database.
Uh what's interesting is that compared
to the elephants, DUTDB's implementation
specializes in the opposite direction.
uh how to query a database, get
information out, not how to put
information in. That's what transaction
processing is all about. So why are we
even doing this experiment?
I mean, we expect the implementation to
be slower, right? Um but the interface
should be more powerful because there's
no network. It's embedded. It's
improcess. No locks across the network.
Stored procedures on steroids. Uh so to
test switching interface like this to
benchmark the speed of light uh we gave
ductb literally a psql file um it's a
batch of transactions one off to the
other to ingest. This takes store
procedures to um you know a whole
another level uh because now the
database has a batch of transactions to
execute. Uh before you know store
procedures are typically executed one
after another. There's no batching. Um
and again this is just a simple
experiment. Um, we we're just trying to
get our intuition, you know, on the
speed up. Any any ideas for what this?
Are we going to go faster? Go slower?
Why would we go faster with an OOLAP
database?
Okay. Interface. Okay, good. So, this
this PQL this Psql batch is 90%
contention. Uh, but duct DB does 2,000
transactions a second. And this is a
column database. uh uh to be clear uh
I'm not trying to recommend you know
duct DB for transaction processing I
don't know what that says about the
others uh
but I I want to show what an embedded
lock free interface can do you know and
of course you could give Postgres a Psql
file too you know and and I'm sure
Postgres would beat this uh but the fact
that DUTDB is not an OOLTP database is
why it's so powerful and interesting I
think as a control. Uh so how does this
compare with Postgress? As soon as you
have 10% contention, the two LGPS they
deteriorate. Even duct DB as an OLAP
database gets 10x more consistent OTP
performance. It's immune to contention
uh at the network level. Uh because the
embedded interface doesn't hold. So
Postgres beats the horizontally scaled
Postgress compatible cluster also costs
a bit less. Uh and this is because the
proprietary cluster holds locks not only
between the client and server but also
across the horizontal partitions uh to
double down on locks across the network
both externally and internally as above
so below. Uh but as you go from 1
millisecond to 10 millisecond roundtrip
OLGP performance drops drastically again
and each time you increase latency.
That's why running multi-reion while
it's advertised uh it's not something
you see often in practice uh
specifically for transaction processing
uh because the coordination across
partitions is too sensitive.
It's too vulnerable to network latency.
So you have to trim your cables. Um and
of course none of this would be a
surprise uh to you if you've read Frank
Mcer's uh scalability but at what cost?
Uh so it's a paper you want not only
your engineering team to read but also
procurement. Uh so to recap we've got
three contestants two with different
implementations the elephants and a
third with a different interface. The
duck gets us the 10x we'd expect also
with store procedures. However with
ductb when we went embedded we went to
the extreme. So we threw out not only
the rollocks uh but the network uh so we
coupled the database to a single server
in the application layer and while this
is fine for analytics and while this
gave us 10x giving up on the network
cost us two things critical uh for OLTP
first we lost multi-achine durability
you can't have your data just on one
machine uh so because there's no network
no replication we need our transactions
to be on more than one database replica
we don't want to lose them. Uh second,
as a result of having lost durability,
we lost availability. Uh without
redundancy, there can be no fault
tolerance and no automated failover if
the primary fails. So is there a way to
fix the interface uh to remove the locks
but keep the network um therefore
preserve durability and thus
availability? If you could design a
database today uh to specialize in
transaction processing, not general
purpose, not analytics, just
transactions, what would it look like?
Better yet, what would you call it? Uh,
of course, as we set out to create
contestant number four, uh, to redesign
the interface for transaction
processing, we must acknowledge
this paper by another Touring Award
winner, the creator of Postgress as well
as the esteemed databaseologist
from CMU, who despite acknowledging SQL
as the prevailing choice for database
management systems, nevertheless
predicted this very talk that we would
claim that the interface of rollocks
across the network is not sufficient for
transaction processing. Of course, we
know that the only reason our professors
do this to tell us not to do these
things is precisely because that's what
they want us to go and do. Uh and
knowing that we would, they even advised
us to learn from history. And so we did.
We went digging and we discovered this.
So according to the winner of the Dutch
Prize for ICT research, Professor Dr.
Hannes Mulesen. This is not a Dutch
biscuit uh but rather the oldest
surviving transaction database 5,000
years old predating language and
demonstrating that while play is
immutable and while durability is
solved, performance will drive databases
to evolve. Uh so what does the future
evolution of transaction processing look
like? Then uh I want to suggest more
like the workload. Uh and here again we
learn from history. Uh for while SQL as
a language has been the language of
databases for a pretty short time, five
decades. Uh the language of debit credit
has been the language of transaction
processing uh at least in the real world
for centuries. Uh so let's start with
the theory do a bit of back of the
envelope. Let's check our workings.
Debit credit over SQL. two round trips
across the network or two milliseconds
per transfer. We're assuming the
database is infinitely fast. Um
what if our interface instead could take
one round trip across the network or one
millisecond but put 8,000 transactions
or debit credits in this query. So let's
even assume a real processing time for
this new design. So it's apples and
oranges intentionally. Um, we're going
to process these 8,000 transactions in
20 millise 20 milliseconds uh for a
total time of 21 milliseconds or two
micros secondsonds per transfer
amortized. Uh, in theory this would give
a,00andx speed up uh even compared to an
infinitely fast database. Um, so how
does this look in practice? Again, uh
recognizing that OLTP is high volume,
high contention, but otherwise routine,
uh we take the essential Jim Gray
information of debit credit, who paid or
gave to who and how much of what and why
and when and where. We take these
essentially two CPU cache lines of
information, 128 bytes. We pack as many
of them as we happen to have at hand or
up to 8,000 of these in a single one
megabyte query. We send this to the
database. Then it processes these
without holding rollocks across the
network acknowledges with a reply in a
single round trip and that's it. So we
almost didn't do anything special. Uh we
studied the theory the workload and the
interface and of course we listen to our
professors. It's so simple. Uh but the
simp the simplicity is composable and
therefore flexible for any kind of
transaction processing whether financial
or non-financial. It's just counting. Uh
so you can imagine that we didn't stop
there but that we might design
everything uh in the database in this
way. So as above so below uh to
co-design everything in the internal
implementation the concurrency control
to amortize the internal latches all
those performance techniques I shared
with you earlier that we would we would
also look at all the interfaces and the
global um consensus protocol the local
storage engine for the entire database
to be purposebuilt like this from the
ground up a brand new modern database in
a language of the future called Zigg
that would become the most powerful
language in the world with the best tool
chain uh and that we' put in all the
performance techniques and all the
static memory allocation assertion and
safety techniques of Tiger style to make
this the fastest safest database that we
could possibly have implemented. But
this is not a talk about implementation
is it? Uh so in theory this interface is
powerful for transaction processing. A
few caveats. It hyper optimizes for one
workload, but it's a widespread workload
OLTP. It's explicitly not a general
purpose or analytics interface. Um,
instead as OOLTP, it doesn't replace
OOLGp or OLAP. It complements them uh
specializing in the counting in the
numbers. So, it's the Olympic 100 meters
and nothing else.
uh one might think that you lose
consistency across your general purpose
and transaction systems now now that you
have two databases but you don't why uh
because you put your user information in
OOLGP you know the filing cabinet and
then the transactions by these users you
put them in OLTP the bank vault uh so
you get a clean separation of concerns
in your architecture olgp is your
control plane database OLTP is your data
plane database and critically also your
system of record. Why? Because it's
updated more frequently. So you hardly
ever change a user's address. You know
the string database is for that you know
rare workload. Uh but when a transaction
comes in if you have any data
dependencies you write these first to
the respective systems and then you
commit the transaction to LTP. If a
transaction is in OLTP you know you have
all the data dependencies. OLTP is your
commit record. Uh so the only question
remaining then uh is now that we have
four contestants,
how do they compare? Uh and how do we
benchmark them? Uh so all the benchmarks
you're about to see, are you getting
nervous now? We're doing benchmarks.
All the benchmarks you're about to see,
uh we're run on the same type of
dedicated AWS instance, the IG6X large.
uh the database server and the data and
the benchmark clients were on separate
instances uh connected by dedicated 37
GB Ethernet link. Uh the client sent
transactions using the database's native
bindings. We executed several warm-up
iterations uh for each scenario to
stabilize caches and buffers followed by
taking multiple measurements for a
stable result. Um we checked a lot of
things. This was weeks of benchmarking.
There's a whole notebook of this uh to
control logical contention uh the number
of transactions using the same hot
account. Uh we generated batches with
that degree of contention. We sent them
concurrently to the database. So it's
just those you know those that Jim Gray
workload we've seen the SQL um and we
just sending that concurrently in. Um we
were careful to adjust the batch sizes
so that we could stay between being open
loop and closed loop. Um the reason is
we didn't want to spike latencies if the
database was clearly not handling the
throughput if it was low throughput. So
we were somewhere between open and
closed loop. A nice nice mix. Um uh
finally we specifically chose Postgres
and compatible databases because
Postgres is so widespread. Uh it you
know it's the it's it is the benchmark.
Uh so we could keep the implementation
anonymous especially for the proprietary
one and we could stay away from
benchmark wars. uh with any specific
commercial vendor. So we always double
down on explaining these performance
ideas from first principles. Uh but I
promised uh that we would put this into
practice uh and as has been uh the trend
at systems distributed performance
benchmarks. So the time has come uh
today
uh to race and
what we're going to do now
is literally we're going to take these
performance traces. We ran all these
databases. Um we collected a performance
trace file. You know a time stamp number
of transactions processed P100 for the
batch. And I'm just going to play these
for you on the screen and we're going to
compare them and see. This is just the
real performance traces that we've
captured. We captured many of them. So
contestant number one, Postgres. Let's
start. Um
um this is the race. We're replaying the
transactions. You can see we're doing
about 300. Uh latency P100 is around 200
millies. Um and this is actually what
we're replaying now in real time. Um, so
Postcrest had its first release in 1996.
Uh, the hardware we're using costs
$4,000 a month. Uh, it's got half a
terabyte of RAM, ton of CPU, huge
network NVMe. You almost want to see the
ref counter.
Uh, so for this trace with 10%
contention, Postgres is doing around
a,000 TPS uh, with a P100 latency of
200. Um, you can see the actual trace
data running. Um there's our latency and
if we slot that real trace data now you
actually see a real dashboard. Um
but you know to be a race we need a
racing driver.
There's Postgrace. I think we need a
racetrack too. And there goes Postgrace
racing by itself getting a head start.
Uh so I think we need another racer
don't you? Who shall we bring in?
[Music]
Tiger Beetle.
So you can see Tiger Beles waiting
patiently at the starting line. Post
Grizz is doing laps.
[Music]
Post is on lap four.
And again, this is the real performance
trace of Postgress. Tiger needles real
performance trace isn't running yet. Um,
but it will start running as uh as soon
as we hit start.
Maybe we wait a while.
[Music]
Post cruise is almost halfway.
So post cruis is on lap six. Should we
start tiger beetle yet?
Yeah. Okay. I think we need a countdown.
So three, two, one.
Catching up a little quickly.
Okay,
so Tiger Beetle's doing 300,000 a
second. That was so fast you almost want
to see a replay.
What's happening?
>> It's coming.
This is the real bus speed from that
dress file. What you're seeing here is
simply re we just put an interface on it
is literally all you're seeing. We we
did have to slow down tiger beetle by
10x in the actual tiger beetle was so
fast we couldn't visualize it for you so
we had to like make it artificially
slower but postgres is realtime speed.
Um yeah so in 10 seconds at 10%
contention uh Tiger Beetle processed 3
million transactions reaching a top
speed of 400,000 transactions a second.
Um,
and you know that's with 20 secondary
indexes enabled for Tiger Beetle. So we
traded some of the million plus TPS that
Tiger Beetle's engine can do. Uh, we
traded some of that for full secondary
indexing here. Worst latency was 305
millise to process 8,000 transactions at
a time. Um, if we' let Postgress keep
racing would have taken 44 minutes.
Postgres top speed,600.
Tiger Beetle is doing full replication
and full consensus. It's running on a
cluster of four machines. Um
so you know it's doing all of that and
it's 266 times than post faster than
Postgres uh which is a single machine
with no replication. Uh so that's why
it's important I think to insist that
our databases are correct and fast. Uh
because if you can design for
performance like this a th00andx
performance then you get more safety not
less. Uh this is the power of an
interface for performance. Uh so the
track we raced was called Super Circuit
um in honor of Gene Amdal who dreamed in
circuits fine just 10% he warned can
choke the line. When lux and latches
stole the rights and speedups fade
despite the mightp
weeps more is not always
right. And that was just 10% contention.
What happens if we dial it up?
What happens if we dial it up to 50%
contention?
Mount Boom. Can you broker the movers
and the shakers? Match the volumes of
the makers. Uh, so I'm sure we could if
we had a Postgress compatible cluster,
right? If we had horizontal scalability,
Postgress cluster. So this remember this
is Postgress. Um, if it ain't
horizontal, it's legacy. Uh, this was
the best hardware we could get. This is
the million-doll cluster. While it's
slightly smaller spec, remember, it's
four times more scalable because we've
got four times as many nodes.
Um, so, and here it is, the McLaren
16 of the biggest machines we could get
to spread the load horizontally. So,
Tiger Beetle's running vertically. It's
got replication across four machines,
but we don't do horizontal scalability.
Tiger Beetle scales vertically with
replication for durability. It's very
simple. Um, so Tiger Beetle, yeah, it's
a quarter of the size of this Postgress
cluster. No sharding. Um,
getting ready.
So just to be sure that Postgress can't
possibly lose, remember this is the
infinite, you know, um, unlimited scale
cluster. Let's be sure that it can't
possibly lose. Let's give We're going to
give it a bit of a head start. Show
respect. I'm just going to plug in a
minute. 42 is the magic number.
Okay. Zero. Great. 42. Great. So, we
we're giving Postcript cluster um a
minute and 42 seconds head start. You
can see it top right. Uh, you ready to
get going on Mount Boom?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Great.
Off goes Postgress Cluster.
Off you go.
We're going to shake the contention in
this in this level to 50%. We're going
to really feel it.
Postgres is doing 100, you know, 100,
let's call it 200 transactions a second.
It's doing 200 transactions a second.
Our company will never need to do that
many transactions. A million dollar
cluster were scalable. Um done 4,000 so
far. Tiger Beetle's waiting at the
starting line. Things are shaking.
[Music]
When we reach the the time, Tiger Dele's
going to start automatically by racer.
So again, you can see bottom left
corner, the racer here. This interface
is literally we're just playing
performance traces. We did a whole lot
of performance benchmarking. We captured
these traces. We're just visualizing it
for you with an interface.
[Music]
Power of an interface for understanding.
Respect to Postgress cluster P100
latency is 100 mills.
But remember, we're tuning the batch
sizes. So we we're only sending in 10
transactions at a time. Otherwise, the
latencies would just spike. They would
break all those SLAs's of like 1 second.
It would be horrible. That's why we can
really only send 10 at a time because
we're trying to be remembered between
open and close loop. Off goes Tiger
Beetle.
No problem with the contention.
[Music]
We've overtaken Postgress.
You can see Tiger Beetle stress file
bottom right. We're able to do uh
batches of 8,000 at a time with the
P100. Pretty similar to Procreate SM
order.
[Music]
Uh so with contention of 50% uh tiger
beetle is not a thousand times faster uh
2,400
times faster uh than the horizontal
Postgres cluster which would have taken
you know a day to do the same number of
transactions. So that's resilience that
it it it tried that hard to keep going.
Of course to be fair to the postcris
cluster it's general purpose or OOLTP it
was not designed for OLTP uh whereas
tiger beetle specializes only in OLTP
and explicitly not for OGP you know it
can't even execute LGP queries so it
can't be benchmarked in reverse uh so
this is the power of an interface for
performance
shall we stop there
one more
Okay,
so that was Mount Boom. 50% contention.
What about Oasis? Uh this is Galactica
transactions at planetary proportions.
This is the power law. 80% transactions
by 20% of users. 90% contention. There
are real systems in the world. For
example, UPI 85% of transactions go
through one row phone pay. Other uh
sorry 50% go through phone pay. The
other 35% through Google pay. two rows
that dominate with 85%.
Um, a lot of these numbers are public
and you can get them. UPI's scale is
staggering. You know, instant payment
system and these systems are spreading
to countries around the world, even to
the US with Fed now. Um, let's see how
we do. Um, so we've raced the two
elephants. Um,
um, and we've seen that Tiger Beetle
beat OLGP. Um, but what about OLAP? What
about an embedded database with no
network or replication at all? So, of
course, for our last race in Amsterdam,
it's got to be DUCD. Uh,
so here, um, DuckDB running on the same
hardware as Tiger Beetle. Tiger Beetle's
doing full replication. DuctTDB isn't.
Uh, Tiger Beetle's got high
availability, consensus, failover, all
of that. Um, and we're going to race the
two at 90% contention. Um
so and because there are quite a few
duct people, duct DB people here in
Amsterdam and mother duck people, I need
to be very careful. We need to be
absolutely certain that ductb wins. Um
so the Postgress cluster got a a minute
head start. That wasn't enough. Uh duct
DB we know is already 10 times faster
than OGP at OLTP. So how much head start
do we need to give DuckDB to be safe?
I'm going to say 10 minutes. What do you
all say?
How many minutes shall we give Duck TV
head start?
>> 20
>> 20 20 20
23 Anyone say more than 23 60 I'm going
with 23.
Okay. How many seconds?
>> 20 25 seconds.
Okay. Well, we committed on 23. Uh, it's
a bit Yeah. How many seconds?
>> 25.
>> 25 seconds.
>> 19.
>> 19. Okay.
And now, um, so it's we're going to have
to wait 23 minutes because that that is
our head start. So, we put a little
feature in this racer. Um, you will be
able to use this race yourself. we will
be releasing it that you can actually
upload your own database trace files and
race different databases or different
systems any kind of system you can race
them on this track. Um it's got the very
cool feature called let's do the time
warp. Uh so we're going to do that
because otherwise we would be sitting
here for 23 minutes. So what's going to
happen is we're going to give duct DB a
little bit of a start and then the racer
itself will figure out from the two
trace files just before you know
contestant number two is going to start
and that's we'll we'll time warp duct DB
to that point. Um
yeah
I heard someone say shame that's a lot
of head start. Okay so yeah for our
third and final race can I get a
countdown?
[Music]
Off goes duct DB. This is a massive
track, massive scale.
So, duct DB is already doing better than
the Postgres clusters. Um, and Postgres
instance 1,800 transactions a second at
90% contention. This is a column
database. This should not be happening.
But duct DB is outperforming OLGP. I
told Hannis on the boat the other day
and he they had never tried this. Uh
they were quite happy. Uh we're about to
do the time warp about a ripple space
time.
There it is. There's the time warp. Uh
DuctTB is now on its last lap, lap 10.
Tiger Beetle still hasn't started.
Uh so duct DB has done nearly 2 million
transactions um after um
after its head start. Um and if you look
uh you know top right there's there's
still about 40 seconds before Tiger
Beal's going to get going. Uh so when
DuctTB gets around the dark side of the
moon uh it's just one stretch to the
finish. It's that last little lap around
the around the moon lap and there's the
finish line.
You can see DuckDB flashing. It's
getting excited like it's it's it's on
its last lap. It's pretty close to the
end.
Countdown with me. 7 6
90% contention. Tiger Beetle's
throughput is the same.
Duct is around the moon. It's
skateboarding into the home stretch.
Uh, Tiger Beetle's third lap is is
complete.
DuctTB is on its last lap.
Tiger Beetle's only halfway.
DuctTB has the finish in sight.
It's about to cross the intersection.
Tiger Be only on lap seven.
DuctTV approaching the finish.
[Music]
This is real performance trace sta.
We're just playing with camera angles in
Blender.
[Music]
So with 90% contention
uh full replication, uh Tiger Be is 229
times faster than duct DB executing a
Psql file in process. Um
and DuctTB is 10 times faster again than
the elephants. So, we got about a 2,000
speed up here
and I think we can we can finish here uh
to rank the contestants
uh tallest
to fastest which is the power of an
interface for performance. It's
[Music]